<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The interest of England in the preservation of Ireland humbly presented to the Parliament of England / by G.P., Esq.</title>
            <author>Philips, George, 1599?-1696.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1689</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 64 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A54704</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P2027</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R1613</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13069989</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13069989</idno>
            <idno type="VID">97108</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A54704)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 97108)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 395:23)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The interest of England in the preservation of Ireland humbly presented to the Parliament of England / by G.P., Esq.</title>
                  <author>Philips, George, 1599?-1696.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[9], 28 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Rich. Chiswell ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1689.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Written by G. Philips. Cf. BM.</note>
                  <note>"Licensed, July 15th, 1689. J. Fraser"</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Ireland --  History --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:97108:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:97108:1"/>
            <p>THE INTEREST OF ENGLAND In the PRESERVATION of <hi>IRELAND.</hi> Humbly Preſented to the PARLIAMENT OF ENGLAND.</p>
            <p>By <hi>G. P.</hi> 
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr>
            </p>
            <q>Nam tua Res agitur, Paries cùm proximus ardet, Et neglecta ſolent Incendia ſumere Vires.</q>
            <floatingText type="license" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>Licenſed, <hi>July</hi> 15th. 1689.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>J. Fraſer.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Rich Chiſwell</hi> at the <hi>Roſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> and <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> St. <hi>Pauls Church-Yard,</hi> MDCLXXX<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:97108:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:97108:2"/>
            <head>TO THE HONOURABLE THE Knights, Citizens, and Burgeſſes IN PARLIAMENT Aſſembled.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> do not in the leaſt preſume to <hi>inform</hi> Your <hi>Judgments,</hi> or to <hi>ſupplicate</hi> your <hi>Charity</hi> by the <hi>Boldneſs</hi> of this <hi>Dedication.</hi> The Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of the Nation cannot be Ignorant of all matters Foreign or Domeſtick, that concern the <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, Safety,</hi> and <hi>Advantage</hi> of <hi>it.</hi> And you have already expreſt ſuch a feeling <hi>Commiſeration</hi> of the Calamities of <hi>Ireland,</hi> that it would ſeem an Offence unpardonable, to ſolicit your <hi>Compaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> by an immodeſt <hi>Importunity.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:97108:3"/>
            <p>You have <hi>Teſtify'd your Tenderneſs,</hi> in promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the <hi>Brief,</hi> and General <hi>Collection,</hi> for the Relief of the Diſtreſſed <hi>Proteſtants</hi> of <hi>Ireland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You have <hi>Signaliz'd your Zeal</hi> to the Proteſtant Intereſt, by a deliberate Contrivance, and a ready Expedition of the <hi>Pole-Bill,</hi> appropriated, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed only for the <hi>Reduction</hi> of <hi>Ireland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You have <hi>Publiſhed your Reſolution</hi> to inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſs your ſelves in the Cauſe of <hi>Ireland,</hi> by a No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Promiſe to ſupply the <hi>KING</hi> with what ſhall be further requiſite for the Recovery of it.</p>
            <p>You have <hi>Vouchſafed a Generous Regard</hi> to a multitude of Exiled Gentlemen (of whom ſome ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonably and prudently withdrew, others with great Hazard and Difficulty eſcaped; but all Voluntarily dſſierted then Houſes and Eſtates, becauſe they would not ſtrengthen the hands of the Papiſts, or contribute to a <hi>French</hi> 
               <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpation or the Excluſion of the Engliſh Right and Title) by deſigning ſome competent Proviſion for their neceſſary Support pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion'd to their reſpective Sufferings; and by ſo affectionate and repeated Addreſſes to His Majeſty in their Favour <hi>(who tho he needs no Interceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion for the Care of His Subjects, yet He loves and delights to ſeem perſwaded by His Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment)</hi> you have made them your <hi>Votaries,</hi> you have obliged them by everlaſting Bonds of Gratitude, and they ſhall be recommended to Posterity as the firſt that ever went under the Honourable Character of <hi>Penſioners to the Parliament.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:97108:3"/>
            <p>You have <hi>demonſtrated your Abhorrence</hi> of all clandestine Practices, by a ſtrict Inquiſition after the Authors and occaſions of the procraſtinated Relief of <hi>Ireland.</hi> and the Miſcarriages of particular Men in their Truſts, and Imployments: Whereby <hi>England,</hi> is put to an <hi>After-game,</hi> and obliged in their own Defence to retrive that <hi>Kingdom,</hi> at the hazard of many Lives, and the Expence of a vaſt Treaſure, which by the very Countenance, and appearance of a ſmall Succour had been <hi>eaſily, cheaply, and ſafely</hi> aſſured and preſerved Nay under your <hi>Protection,</hi> I will ſpeak out the <hi>Truth:</hi> When <hi>London Derry</hi> had ſhut their Gates againſt the Iriſh, and <hi>Iniskillin</hi> ſoon after refuſed to admit a <hi>Popiſh Garriſon;</hi> when the Proteſtants in <hi>Dublin</hi> were Numerous, Rich and Stout; when in <hi>Munſter,</hi> the <hi>Earl of Inchiquin</hi> (with many others) was very apprehenſive of the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent danger, and ready with the leaſt Aſſiſtance from <hi>England,</hi> to ſecure the <hi>Proteſtant Intereſt</hi> there: When the <hi>Lord Kingſton</hi> in <hi>Conaght</hi> out ſtript the <hi>Deputy,</hi> and made up his Muſters of Horſe and Foot before him: when forty thouſand brisk men were upon Watch and Ward in <hi>Ulſter;</hi> and the Earl of <hi>Tyrconnel</hi> (utterly irreſclute what Meaſures to take) ſaid to a Perſon of Honour (who urged him to lay down the Sword, and Submit to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) <hi>What would you have me do? I ſee no Commiſſion to demand the Sword, would you have me caſt it over the Caſtle Walls?</hi> I ſay in this Juncture, any one eminent Perſon, attended with a ſmall Party, and furniſhed with a reaſonable Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion of Arms and Mony, had without blows, or
<pb facs="tcp:97108:4"/>ſlaughter, ſecured the Kingdom of <hi>Ireland,</hi> in their Allegiance to the preſent <hi>King and Queen;</hi> and with much Eaſe prevented, and curbed the inſultory <hi>Inſurrections in Scotland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But alas! while the <hi>Parliament</hi> are buſie in <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſing,</hi> and <hi>debating</hi> the Buſineſs of <hi>Ireland,</hi> the <hi>Clergy</hi> are for the moſt Part <hi>ſilent;</hi> the one <hi>Votes</hi> for them, but I do not hear, that the other <hi>Prays</hi> for them; the miſeries of <hi>Ireland</hi> are Remembred in the <hi>Parliament-Houſe,</hi> but Seldom <hi>mentioned in the Pulpit;</hi> being omitted in their Addreſſes to the <hi>Throne of Mercy,</hi> by a very regardleſs <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For my Part, I had neither taken upon me the Confidence to make this <hi>Addreſs,</hi> nor given the world the Trouble of this undigeſted <hi>Pamphlet</hi> (hudled o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver in haſt, and without the Advantages of Study, Books, Advice, or Retirement) but that a ſort of Men no way conſiderable in number, or Intereſt, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe in their <hi>Humor,</hi> as Flattering in their judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, aſſume a Liberty to retail their raw and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concocted Notions in <hi>Coſſee-Houſes</hi> (where Men pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend a Priviledge, <hi>to ſay any thing but their Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers)</hi> and with as little <hi>Charity</hi> as <hi>Diſcretion,</hi> to arraign the <hi>Judgment,</hi> and cenſure the <hi>Actions</hi> of the <hi>Iriſh Proteſtant-Refuges,</hi> and ſeverely to up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braid them with their <hi>Baniſhment</hi> and <hi>Poverty,</hi> as the diſſerved Effects of their own <hi>Perverſneſs,</hi> in not Submitting to him; who deſerted the principal Kingdom, and reſtleſs himſelf in that which is Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate. Nay, ſome have proceeded to that degree of uncharitable Frenzy, that they have belched out
<pb facs="tcp:97108:4"/>their balſphemous Curſes on <hi>poor bleeding Ireland:</hi> Sinking it into the Sea with their <hi>Execrations,</hi> and diſparaging it as an <hi>incomber'd Eſtate, not worth the Redemption.</hi> Would God! it might pleaſe the <hi>King</hi> to undeceive this murmuring <hi>Crew,</hi> by Commanding them on the <hi>Expedition</hi> with <hi>Duke Schomberg,</hi> or <hi>Count Solmes;</hi> that they may ſee the Country they ſo much <hi>deſpiſe,</hi> and be convinced how little Reaſon they had to undervalue it. And I am humbly of Opinion, that it would conduce much to the regaining that Kingdom, if the King would think it fit, to imploy the <hi>Gentlemen</hi> of that Country upon that Service. It is not to be imagin'd, how far <hi>Loyalty, whetted with ſelf-Intereſt,</hi> will go, or what Exploits may be performed by ſuch as fight with a <hi>double Courage,</hi> to <hi>ſerve the King,</hi> and <hi>to recover their Own.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus far I have <hi>pleaded</hi> for my <hi>Country,</hi> let me now be a <hi>Suitor for my ſelf.</hi> If a glowing <hi>Zeal,</hi> for <hi>Religion;</hi> an anxious <hi>Sympathy</hi> with my <hi>Friends;</hi> and a <hi>pungent ſenſe</hi> of my own <hi>Sufferings</hi> have tranſported me into any <hi>Impertinency:</hi> I humbly implore <hi>Pardon</hi> from the <hi>Honourable Houſe of Commons,</hi> for the <hi>Rudeneſs</hi> of this <hi>Addreſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>George Philips.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:97108:5"/>
            <head>The Intereſt of <hi>England</hi> in the Preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Ireland.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">From theſe Conſiderations.</head>
            <list>
               <item>I. The Advantage to the Kingdom of <hi>England</hi> in general.
<list>
                     <item>1. By the Revenue.</item>
                     <item>2. The Fertility, and Plenty.</item>
                     <item>3. The Number.</item>
                     <item>4. The Religion.</item>
                     <item>5. The Conſanguinity, and Aſſinity.</item>
                     <item>6. The Imployments Eccleſiaſtical, Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil and Military.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>II. The Advantage to the Trade of <hi>England.</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. By the Scituation.</item>
                     <item>2. The Exportation.</item>
                     <item>3. The Importation.</item>
                     <item>4. The Ingenuity of the Inhabitants.</item>
                     <item>5. The Benefit to the KING.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>III. The Danger of falling into the Hands of the <hi>French.</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. By Ingroſſing all Trade.</item>
                     <item>2. By Intercepting the Trade of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>3. By Interrupting the Peace of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:97108:5"/>
            <head>THE Intereſt of ENGLAND, IN THE Preſervation of IRELAND.</head>
            <div type="introduction">
               <head>The Introduction.</head>
               <p>THERE were two things which mainly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributed to the Ruine and Deſolation of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and reduced it to that deplorable Condition, under which it now languiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth; <hi>Reſiſtance,</hi> and <hi>Non-Reſiſtance.</hi> The latter ſprung from a fond and tame ſubmiſſion to the Arbitrary Government <hi>in Ireland;</hi> the other was occaſion'd by a vain and fruitleſs Expectation of <hi>Relief from England.</hi> If the People of that Country had not been over-laviſh in their <hi>Loyalty,</hi> they had not been ſo unfortunate in their <hi>Oppoſition.</hi> In the Reign of <hi>King JAMES,</hi> they were <hi>unreaſonably paſſive;</hi> in the Reign of <hi>King WILLIAM</hi> they have been <hi>unproſperouſly active.</hi> Strange Fate! To be <hi>Loſers</hi> by the One, and not to be <hi>Gainers</hi> by the Other! To be <hi>poſſeſt</hi> of their Eſtates under a <hi>Popiſh Prince;</hi> and to be <hi>kept out</hi> of them un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a <hi>Proteſtant!</hi> Had they been independent, and truſted to their <hi>own Legs,</hi> poſſibly they had ſtood firm
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:97108:6"/>at this Day: but they are miſerably overthrown, by leaning too much on <hi>their Supporters.</hi> If there were any room in our Church for Merits, the Proteſtants of <hi>Ireland</hi> would be intituled to a great Stock, for ſuffering under <hi>King JAMES;</hi> and for <hi>acting</hi> under <hi>King WIELIAM:</hi> but alas! they are <hi>deſpiſed</hi> for the one, and <hi>derided</hi> for the other: ſo difficult a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it is to walk ſteddily upon the uneven ſurface of ſublunary Places; here you encounter a <hi>Precipice,</hi> there a <hi>Quagmire:</hi> That very way which ſeemed the direct Road to Safety and Tranquility, may perhaps lead you into inextricable Troubles, and often ends in certain Miſery and Deſtruction.</p>
               <p>When the Late King (in purſuance of his Deſign to <hi>ſubvert that Church,</hi> which He complemented with the Character of <hi>Loyalty,</hi> and as ſolemnly <hi>promiſed to defend and ſupport it</hi>) was ſo far diſtracted by per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious Counſel, to proſtitute the Kingdom of <hi>Ireland</hi> to the licentious Will of a <hi>Jeſuitical Tyranny;</hi> and to make an Eſſay of ſetling that Idolatrous Worſhip there, which was too early, and unſeaſonable for Him to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt in <hi>England:</hi> when the Sword was put into the Hands of a bigotted Zealot, and more than a million of <hi>Britiſh Proteſtants</hi> ſubjected to the Dominion of an <hi>Iriſh Papiſt;</hi> there was no Murmur heard, no muti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous Whiſpers ſpread abroad to diſcompoſe the People, or affront the Government: men ſigh'd, and ſubmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; they groaned, and gave Obedience, with a pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient Reſignation to the Will of God, and the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of the King: The Proteſtants through the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom were diſarm'd; the Officers of the Army were diveſted of their Commiſſions; the <hi>Soldiers</hi> disbanded and caſhier'd, ſtript and diſarm'd, without demanding a Reaſon for ſuch unwarrantable Dealings, or diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:97108:6"/>the Pleaſure of their Superiors: the <hi>Papiſts</hi> were obtruded into the <hi>Privy Council,</hi> and Chief Miniſtry of State; all Juſtices of the Peace were ſuperſeded, who did not carry <hi>the Mark of the Beaſt:</hi> the <hi>Publick Revenue</hi> committed to ſuch Hands, as would ſurely imploy and improve it to the ſinal extirpation of <hi>Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks;</hi> yet all things proceeded in a ſilent Calm, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Noiſe, or Grumbling: where Maſs houſes were erected, and publickly frequented; no man offer'd to <hi>pull down their Altars:</hi> where the Fryers walk'd the Streets in their uncouth Habits; no man <hi>threw Dirt at them:</hi> the Popiſh Religion was <hi>prohibited by Law;</hi> yet never <hi>contravened by Force:</hi> The People abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted that Superſtitious Way; yet never expreſt their Reſentments by Rage, or Diſcontent: The Charters of their Towns and Corporations were condemned and vacated; yet no ſpark of Sedition was kindled among the Inhabitants: The famous <hi>Act of Settlement</hi> was daily eluded; Poſſeſſion and Property were no ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Guard againſt <hi>Iriſh</hi> Incroachments; yet no man incurr'd the Penalty of a <hi>forcible Deteiner:</hi> the <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Non-reſiſtance</hi> (which was ſo frequently <hi>preach'd</hi> in other Places) was there actually and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally <hi>practiſed;</hi> and <hi>Obedience</hi>) if there be not a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction in the Terms) was truly <hi>paſſive.</hi> Thus poſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing themſelves under the Covert of Privacy, and Retirement, they ſilently expected a Day of Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance from the Appointment of Heaven, without the interpoſition of any Humane Machinations.</p>
               <p>In this Poſture Affairs ſtood in <hi>Ireland,</hi> during tho <hi>ſhort</hi> (if it had not been <hi>ſharp</hi>) Reign of <hi>King JAMES:</hi> and ſo probably they had continued, at leaſt for ſome time, after the miraculous Revolution in <hi>England.</hi> But He, having <hi>Abdicated the Government,</hi> and <hi>deſerted the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:97108:7"/>Throne,</hi> and unnaturally truckt One Kingdom with that Chriſtian Monſter of <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Barbarity, for the empty Hopes of re-poſſeſſing the other Two; it ſeem'd convenient to his <hi>Iriſh Baſhaw,</hi> and the Jeſuitic <hi>Cabal,</hi> to make ſure of a retreating Place, and that of Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity muſt be <hi>Ireland;</hi> which having formerly been given to the Pope, and by him transferred to the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> muſt now be ſold, or mortgaged to the <hi>French</hi> Uſurper; to facilitate whoſe Entry by remov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all Obſtacles, the preſent Poſſeſſors muſt be put out of Doors, that ſo <hi>Livery and Seiſin</hi> might be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, in imitation of the <hi>due Form of Law.</hi> Hereupon Plots were invented; ſeveral Proteſtant Gentlemen were committed to Priſon, Indicted, and Tryed for their Lives; abundance of Commiſſions were iſſued, and the Army multiplied into many Regiments of Horſe and Foot; for whoſe Entertainment, there being no Fund of a growing Revenue, the Goods of the Proteſtants were conſigned to their ſubſiſtence; which they did not pilfer by Night, but drove away whole Flocks and Herds at Noon-day; and in caſe of Reſiſtance, ſecuring their Prey by the Murder of the Owners. Thus the Province of <hi>Munſter</hi> was expoſed to a Military Execution: <hi>Conaught</hi> was entirely plunder'd; and had not the Gates of <hi>London<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derry</hi> been opportunely ſhut, when a Regiment of <hi>Iriſh</hi> were ready to enter it, all <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lſter</hi> had been un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſame Fate, and probably had been followed by an Univerſal <hi>Maſſacre.</hi> But the ſurprizing News of the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi>'s Adventure, and the total Excluſion of Popery and Arbitrary Government in <hi>England,</hi> awakened the Proteſtants in <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lſter</hi> to ſtand upon their Guard; and animated them with an Aſſurance, That <hi>their Redemption was drawing nigh;</hi> flattering them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:97108:7"/>with a Confidence, That as they were under the <hi>Laws</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> ſo they ſhould be no leſs under their <hi>Protection.</hi> They firmly believed, that the ſame methods would be taken in <hi>Ireland,</hi> which had been ſo ſucceſsfully practiſed in <hi>England;</hi> every puff of a fair Wind, revived them with a ſmiling expectation of Succor; they were eager to retrieve their droop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Religion from the Jaws of Death; and ready to rally under a Proteſtant Standard; their Numbers were very conſiderable, and their Courage great; but they were naked and undiſciplin'd, they wanted an Expert Leader; and no Aid appear'd to ſupport them: The Deputy having too ſure and quick Intelligence of the Tranſactions in the Court of <hi>England,</hi> and the dilatory Proceedings there, poured a mighty Army into the Bowels of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lſter,</hi> who rifling the deſerted Houſes, ſeizing and carrying away all portable Goods, and exerciſing all Cruelty on ſuch as did not ſubmit to their Protection, they marched (or rather chaſed the affrighted People) without Interruption, till they received a ſlight <hi>Check</hi> at <hi>Colrane,</hi> and were ſhameful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>bafled</hi> at <hi>Londonderry.</hi> But all the Towns and Forts through the Kingdom (except that <hi>sturdy place,</hi> and its neighbour <hi>Eniskilling</hi>) being Gariſon'd by Papiſts, no Arms nor Horſes permitted to remain with any Proteſtants, (whoſe enjoyment of their Lives was wholly precarious, and reverſible at the will of mercileſs men); all things concurred to advance the long-hatch'd Deſign, which now began to ripen; and King <hi>James,</hi> with a Rabble of <hi>French</hi> Reformers, intermixt with a ſew <hi>Renegado-Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Scotch,</hi> landed among his dearly-beloved <hi>Iriſh</hi> Catholics, where he remains under Pupilage to the <hi>French;</hi> He the Reputed <hi>King,</hi> and Monſieur <hi>d' Avaux</hi> the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:97108:8"/>
               <p>I need not place any Remarks upon the ſupine <hi>Negligence</hi> and fatal <hi>Indifferency</hi> demonſtrated by <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> in their cold Concernment, and ſlow Motions toward the Recovery of <hi>Ireland;</hi> it is obvious to eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry eye; and if any have been wilfully acceſſory to the Ruin and Depopulation of ſo flouriſhing a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, everlaſting Vengeance will purſue them: I wiſh the good People of <hi>England</hi> may ſee in the Mirror of our Misfortunes, that Scheme of <hi>Miſery</hi> and <hi>Confuſion</hi> which was prepared for them, and which aſſuredly will be re-acted on their <hi>Theatre,</hi> if ever the <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Iriſh</hi> be permitted to <hi>tread the Stage.</hi> To unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive that giddy ſort of men, who think to <hi>gather Grapes from Thiſtles;</hi> to enjoy the Profeſſion of the Proteſtant Religion under a Popiſh Ring, and the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration of Jeſuits; to continue in Peace and Safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in this Kingdom, if the other be torn from it; I offer the following Conſiderations; which, weigh'd impartially, may help to convince all ſorts of men, That it is not only the <hi>Interest of</hi> England <hi>to preſerve</hi> Ireland, but that it is neceſſary for their <hi>ſelf-preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> to uſe all imaginable Induſtry and Expedition to reduce it to its former State and Condition.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:97108:8"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>I.</hi> The Advantage to the Kingdom of <hi>ENGLAND</hi> in General.</head>
               <p>I Expect to be abſolved from the Imputation of Flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery and Partiality, when I take upon me to make this aſſeveration; That nothing out of <hi>England</hi> doth, or can rationally conduce more to the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, Wealth, and Proſperity of that Kingdom, than the Addition and Conjunction of <hi>Ireland:</hi> A Country abounding with all things that contribute to Pleaſure and Comfort, and richly endowed with the Bleſſings of Heaven and Earth; ſcituated by Nature as a Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtern-gate to <hi>England; by which</hi> ſhe may diſcharge all manner of Commodities which are ſupernumerary or unneceſſary, to the great encouragement of Naviga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Trade; and <hi>through which</hi> an entrance is given for a continual ſupply of ſuch things as the One may ſtand in <hi>need</hi> of, and the other may conveniently <hi>ſpare.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I ſhall endeavour to make good this Aſſertion, by ſubdividing this Conſideration into the following par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. <hi>The Revenue.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>The Fertility and Plenty.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. <hi>The Number.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>4. <hi>The Religion.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>5. <hi>The Conſanguinity and Affinity.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>6. <hi>The Employments Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical, Civil, and Military.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>I propoſe theſe as ſo many irrefragable Arguments, to convince the World, That the Kingdom of <hi>Ireland</hi> has not only a Self-ſufficiency within it to ſubſiſt without dependency, and to grow rich by its own
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:97108:9"/>peculiar Traffick; but alſo, that by being annexed to <hi>England,</hi> ſubjected to the Government, and incorpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated into its Religion and Laws; it extends the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion, ſtrengthens the Hands, and augments the Wealth of that happy and renowned Nation. <hi>Firſt,</hi> let us take notice of the Revenue.</p>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>I.</hi> The REVEN<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>E.</head>
                  <p>The Revenue of <hi>Ireland</hi> was under a ſenſible decli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation from the commencement of the late King's Reign, occaſioned by the daily <hi>Decay of Trade,</hi> and that by the diſcouragement given to <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> thro' whoſe hands almoſt the whole Commerce and cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Money was wont to circulate; and at length was ſo viſibly impaired, that in the year 1688. the Publick Treaſury was utterly exhauſted; and I have no reaſon to believe that it has ſince that time been recruited by any conſiderable Imburſements, (for I ſuppoſe the <hi>French Money</hi> is in a Treaſury diſtinct, and iſſuable only at the diſcretion of the <hi>French Dictator,</hi> whoſe Orders are not to open his Treaſure, till they land in <hi>England:</hi>) Therefore I deduce my Remarks from the latter end of the Reign of <hi>Charles the Second,</hi> about which time the Publick Revenue was managed by Commiſſioners ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by the King, by whoſe Diligence and Applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion it was notably improved; and it conſiſted in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Branches, as,
<list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Crown-Rents.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Quit-Rents.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Cuſtoms and Exciſe.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Inland-Exciſe.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Hearth-Money.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Wine and Ale Licenſes.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Fines and Forfeitures.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Firſt-Fruits,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>of the Clergy.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list> All which did amount, <hi>communibus Annis,</hi> to about <hi>Three Hundred and forty thouſand Pounds.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:97108:9"/>
                  <p>Out of this Fund was derived the Maintenance and <hi>Pay of an Army,</hi> conſiſting of ſeven Regiments of Foot, three of Horſe, and one of Dragoons: <hi>Exhibitions to the Judges</hi> ſedent, and itinerant, and to all other Officers of the Civil Liſt: a noble Allowance to the <hi>Chief Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor,</hi> a competent Salary to the <hi>Lord Chancellor,</hi> and all the Officers of State: a large Proviſion for all other Charges neceſſary, or contingent: and upon the Audit of the whole Receipts and Disburſements, a very conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable ſum remain'd, moſt of which was remitted into <hi>England,</hi> ſome diſpoſed of in <hi>Ireland,</hi> for <hi>Penſions, Secret Service,</hi> and other Occaſions, at the King's Will and Pleaſure.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>II.</hi> The Fertility, and Plenty.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ireland</hi> doth abound with an Exuberance of Plenty in all things conducing to a pleaſant, and comfortable Living. The Ground, without the Midwifery of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Art, <hi>brings forth Graſs for the Cattel, and Herbs for the uſe of man</hi> in great Abundance; but where the Husbandman hath clubb'd his Invention and Labour, it is rather luxuriant, rendring a mighty Increaſe of all ſorts of Grain, very ſound, and very good Indeed, Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture hath open'd her Stores, and, like a kind Mother, hath liberally beſtow'd her Bleſſings on that Iſland; The Earth ſeems to ſtand in Competition with the Water for the Pre-eminence: the one overloaded with its own Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct; the other, overſtockt by its proper Inhabitants: the infinite Store of Corn of all ſorts, the pleaſant Studds of Horſes and Mares, the numerous Herds of Cattel, the vaſt Flocks of Sheep (in moſt Places exceeding thoſe of <hi>England</hi> in their Size) is even to admiration: neither do I brag, when I ſay, that the <hi>beſt Parts of Ireland</hi> are in every Reſpect (except the Improvement) equal to the <hi>beſt Parts in England;</hi> and that the <hi>worſt Parts</hi> of it are
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:97108:10"/>not ſo bad and barren as the <hi>worſt Parts</hi> of the other: Or when I challenge <hi>England</hi> it ſelf to ſhew ſo vaſt a Tract of rich and excellent Land lying together, as is to be ſeen from <hi>Carlingford</hi> all the way to <hi>Dublin,</hi> from thence (excluding the Mountains of <hi>Wicklow</hi>) to <hi>Carlow;</hi> from thence through part of <hi>Queens</hi> and <hi>Kings</hi> County, ſo croſs the <hi>Shannon,</hi> and round by <hi>Longford</hi> to <hi>Roſcommon:</hi> in which vaſt Tract of Land, at leaſt fourſcore Miles ſquare, there is not ſo much barren Land, as is to be found in two Shires only in <hi>England</hi> (and not far from <hi>London</hi>) <hi>Berkſhire</hi> and <hi>Surrey.</hi> The Seas are plentifully ſtor'd with Fiſh of all Kinds, and the Markets ſupply'd with ſuch Plenty and Variety, as might ſatiate the Luxu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and Prodigality of <hi>Lucullus:</hi> the Loughs are fill'd with Pike, Breme, Pearch, Roach, and Trouts; but the Freſh Rivers ſwarm with ſtupendious Quantities. If men (as juſtly they may) ſhall become doubtful, ſcrupulous, and incredulous, when I make mention of the extraordinary <hi>Pilchard-Fiſhings</hi> in the <hi>South,</hi> and the <hi>Herring-Fiſhings</hi> in the <hi>North;</hi> my Credit will certainly run a great Riſque, and my Veracity be ſuſpected, when I relate the <hi>Won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of the Deep,</hi> and come to ſpeak of the Prodigious <hi>Fiſhings</hi> for <hi>Salmon</hi> and <hi>Eels</hi> in the Rivers of <hi>Lough-foyl,</hi> and the <hi>Bann.</hi> If men will ſtartle at the Report of ſix thouſand Barrels of <hi>Pilchards</hi> made in one year upon the Coaſt of the County of <hi>Cork;</hi> or to hear, that in ſome Parts of <hi>Conaught</hi> they take ſo great Draughts of them, that, not being provided of Salt to cure them, they lay them in heaps, and manure the Land with them: that (beſide the plentiful Fiſhing of Herrings in and about the Bay of <hi>Dublin,</hi> the <hi>Skerryes, Carlingford,</hi> and all the Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thern Coaſt) they have uſually made and ſent away in one year two thouſand Tuns of Herrings from the ſingle Fiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at <hi>Dunfanaghan:</hi> then undoubtedly they will ſmile, and ridicule me, when I tell them, That there is made
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:97108:10"/>commonly five hundred Tuns of Salmon in a year, in <hi>Loghfoyl,</hi> and the <hi>Bann,</hi> and other Rivers in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Londonderry;</hi> that beſides the Royal Piſcary of the <hi>Bann,</hi> there are between <hi>Colrane</hi> and <hi>Loghneagh</hi> ſeven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Salmon-Fiſhings; that there are the ſame round about that Lough, which is ſixty Miles in Compaſs; that at the Leap of <hi>Colrane,</hi> ten Tuns of Salmon have been ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken at one Draught of a Net: That the laſt year at the <hi>Grebbin,</hi> twelve Miles beyond <hi>Londonderry,</hi> two and thirty Hogſheads of Salmon were taken at once, and for want of room in their Boats, a great part of them thrown again into the River: That in the <hi>Eel-weres,</hi> in the River of <hi>Bann,</hi> fourſcore thouſand <hi>Eels</hi> have been catcht in one Night. But I have ſpoken modeſtly, and within compaſs, and there are too many Witneſſes (much againſt their wills) now in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> who can confirm the Truth of what I have declared. I am loth to paſs by the <hi>Salmon-Pound</hi> (commonly call'd the <hi>Cutt</hi>) near <hi>Colrane,</hi> becauſe, as I conceive, ſuch ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thing is not in the World: It is a great Trough, made like a Tanner's Vat, about fifty foot long, twenty foot wide, and ſix deep; a Stream of the River of <hi>Bann</hi> runs through it, and at the Place where the Water en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, a row of Stakes are placed very near together, like a Rack in a Stable; at the other end of the <hi>Cutt</hi> a parcel of ſharp Spikes are cluſtered together, very cloſe at the Point, and wide at the Head, ſo that the Salmons (who always ſwim againſt the Stream) and other Fiſh, may get in at pleaſure, but can neither return the way they went in, nor get out at the other end; whereby it hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens, that <hi>on Monday morning</hi> (there being a reſpite to Fiſhing all <hi>Sunday,</hi> and none taken out of the <hi>Cutt</hi> with their Loops) a Stranger would be aſtoniſh'd to ſee an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable company of Fiſh riding on the backs of one another, even to the top of the Water, and with
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:97108:11"/>great eaſe, and pleaſant Divertiſement, taken up in Loops.</p>
                  <p>All theſe prodigious Quantities of Fiſh are but collected for the Uſe of <hi>England;</hi> to whoſe Ports, or to whoſe Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, they are yearly conſigned, and diſtributed.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>III.</hi> The N<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>MBER.</head>
                  <p>Having had no Buſineſs, or Imployment, which might adminiſter an Opportunity to inſpect the Catalogues and Returns of Pariſhes and Counties, or to view the Poll-Books; it will not be poſſible for me to make any other than a conjectural Calculation of the Number of <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Inhabitants in Ireland.</hi> But by a modeſt Computa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion I may adventure to aver, That at the beginning of the Reign of the Late King, there were in the City of <hi>Dublin,</hi> and the Four Provinces, above <hi>a Million of Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh Proteſtants.</hi> I am confirm'd in this Suppoſition by a ſad Reflection upon the Paſſages in the Year 1641. at which time the Number of the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> was very in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiderable in compariſon with the <hi>Natives;</hi> and poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly did not amount to the Half of what they were in 1681. yet even then above <hi>two hundred thouſand,</hi> naked and defenceleſs People, were maſſacred in cold Blood, and barbarouſly murther'd without Provocation, or Reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance. I reckon, that when the late Revolution hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, there were <hi>two hundred thouſand men</hi> fit to carry Arms, bound to the Intereſt of <hi>England</hi> by the Obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of <hi>Religion, Love, Loyalty</hi> and <hi>Blood;</hi> who may be beneficial in their Service and Aid, when it ſhall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired; though of late (by the apparent Judgment of God) they have been terrified by them, on whom they alway had an awe; routed by ſuch, whoſe Strength they d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3+ letters">
                        <desc>•••…</desc>
                     </gap>ed; and diſpoſſeſt of their Eſtates, without ſtrugling for their Property.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:97108:11"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>IV.</hi> The RELIGION.</head>
                  <p>Among all the preſſing Motives, that recommend the Care and Conſervation of <hi>Ireland,</hi> there is no one more cogent, than the Conſideration of the <hi>Religion</hi> there <hi>eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh'd by Law:</hi> which reaſonably ought to intereſs all good Chriſtians in a feeling-Sympathy and Concernment for them; and thereby the People of <hi>England</hi> have a fit Opportunity, at once equally to exert their <hi>Duty to God, and Charity to their Brethren.</hi> It is true, the Proteſtant Religion was not univerſally profeſs'd through the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, neither were all who were diſtinguiſh'd by that Character, perfectly cemented; the Papiſts were nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous in every County, (tho leaſt of all in <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lster);</hi> yet Popery ſeemed to be rather <hi>Hereditary</hi> than <hi>Elective;</hi> to be more the Reſult of Education, than Judgment; inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much, as it became like a <hi>Logical Property</hi> to the Natives, and <hi>Papiſt</hi> and <hi>Iriſh man</hi> were Terms convertible: So great an Influence has <hi>Cuſtom</hi> over all the Faculties of Mind and Body; they put on Religion as a faſhionable Garment, the Dictate of the Prieſt warranting the mode; and thick Ignorance inflames their Devotion. Nevertheleſs the Proteſtant Religion was predominant; Popery <hi>ſneak'd to the Mountains,</hi> and <hi>ſquatted behind the Buſhes;</hi> the Maſs was not known, nor a Fryar ſeen, till by the Influence of the <hi>Late King,</hi> and the furious Zeal of his Deputy, things were changed as it were in a moment, and all Commands Civil and Military, committed to the Hands of <hi>Papiſts.</hi> But when, by the Bleſſing of God, and the Aſſiſtance of <hi>England,</hi> that poor haraſſed Country ſhall be reſtored to its <hi>former State and Condition,</hi> it will be a joyful Reflection for their Brethren and Benefactors, to hear of ſo many Thouſand Perſons united with them in the ſame Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as in all other Reſpects and Concernments.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="section">
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:97108:12"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>V.</hi> The Conſanguinity and Aſſinity.</head>
                  <p>The Inhabitants of <hi>Ireland,</hi> (excluding the Natives of the Land, who always were, and ever will be <hi>Thorns in our Sides;</hi> and who, ſince the firſt Conqueſt of them, were never able to accompliſh that Deſign which was bequeath'd from Generation to Generation, till this late unhappy Juncture) do not derive their Pedigree from Strangers; they are the legitimate Offspring of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland;</hi> there is ſcarce a Man there of Britiſh Extraction, except ſuch as by very long continuance are degenerated into mere <hi>Iriſh,</hi> but in one of thoſe King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms will Challenge a Father, Brother, or near Kinſman. They are not eſtranged in their Language, Habit, Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, or Cuſtoms; they retain the natural Propenſions diſſeminated from their reſpective Families, and own a filial Reverence to their Countries, as to their lawful <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents</hi> (not their <hi>Step mothers</hi>) who not being able to make a competent Proviſion for all their <hi>Iſſue</hi> at home, have ſent ſome of their <hi>Children</hi> abroad, to ſeek for their Livelihood on the other <hi>ſide of the Ferry;</hi> where in their Manners and Humour, they bear an exact Reſemblance to that Original, whereof they are the Tranſcript; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept only in their profuſe <hi>Hoſpitality,</hi> and luxurious Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption of Meat and Drink (to which, perhaps, they are inclined by the Conſtitution of the Air, or diſpoſed by the Genius of the Country, or tempted by the incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible <hi>Plenty</hi> and <hi>Cheapneſs</hi> of all ſorts of Proviſions) yet in their Language they have gone beyond their Teachers, having refined the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Tongue from the odd Tones, and uncouth words uſed in ſeveral Counties diſtant from <hi>London;</hi> and reformed the <hi>Scotch</hi> from the Clowniſh Dialect ſpoken by the vulgar People. So that the People of <hi>England</hi> are bound in Conſcience and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Reaſon, to regard the <hi>Engliſh</hi> in <hi>Ireland,</hi> as <hi>Bone of their Bone,</hi> and <hi>Fleſh of their Fleſh;</hi> and the <hi>Scots</hi> as na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turalized
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:97108:12"/>and incorporated with them, to ſympathize with them in their <hi>Sufferings,</hi> to participate in their <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventures,</hi> and from the Principles of <hi>Generoſity,</hi> as well as the Impulſe of <hi>Nature,</hi> and a prudential <hi>Foreſight</hi> of the ſame Calamities hovering over their Heads, to uſe their utmoſt Effort to re-aſſure that Kingdom in its <hi>Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendage</hi> to <hi>England,</hi> and abſolutely to eradicate the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Papiſts and all <hi>French</hi> Intruders.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>VI.</hi> The Imployments, Eccleſiaſtical, Civil and Military.</head>
                  <p>Since <hi>England</hi> is bounded by the Sea, and cannot be inlarged by the Diſcovery of any <hi>Newfound Land;</hi> ſince the Inhabitants are as fruitful as the Soil, Prolific, and continually multiplying and increaſing; ſince the Vigor and Generoſity of their Temper, ſpurs them on to <hi>Buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Activity;</hi> and that the Liſt of <hi>Places, Offices and Preferments</hi> in Church and State, do bear no Proportion with the number of <hi>Competitors, Candidates, and Preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders:</hi> It is an unexpreſſible Benefit and Advantage, that they can ſo eaſily inlarge their Quarters, and ſpread through a Kingdom in Polity <hi>Subordinate,</hi> but in natural Fertility no way <hi>Inferior</hi> to that from whence they ſprang. I think it very well worth the Obſervation, That among all the <hi>Biſhops, Deans,</hi> and <hi>Dignitaries</hi> in the Church of <hi>Ireland,</hi> (in the firſt year of the late King) ſo very few were born in that Kingdom, but almoſt all of them tranſplanted from <hi>England;</hi> ſo were the <hi>Lord Chancellor, Lord Chief Baron, Attorny General,</hi> and many of the Judges and Officers in the Civil Liſt; by ſuch alſo, was the <hi>Revenue</hi> managed. And for the Army, it was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly a <hi>Detachment</hi> out of the ſeveral <hi>Shires in England.</hi> In a word, there did <hi>Divines</hi> and Scholars get <hi>Prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;</hi> Lawyers, Attornies, and others of the <hi>Long Robe,</hi> met with <hi>Practice and Promotion; Clerks, Accountants,</hi> and Men of ingenious Education, were gratified with <hi>Imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments;</hi>
                     <pb n="16" facs="tcp:97108:13"/>the younger Sons of the <hi>Engliſh Nobility and Gentry,</hi> were honoured with <hi>Military Commands;</hi> and thouſands of the meaner ſort train'd up in the Diſcipline of War. All which muſt have met with a Check in their Fortunes, and been ſubjected to a leſs generous courſe of Living, and remain'd as <hi>Shrubs</hi> in their own Soil; while by this <hi>Tranſplantation</hi> they grow up to tall Trees, ſhoot out their Branches, and bring forth abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant of Fruit.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Advantage to the Trade of <hi>England.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Hitherto I have endeavoured by a few ſhort Hints, to repreſent the many valuable Benefits and Advantages ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cruing to the Kingdom of <hi>England</hi> in general, by the Conjunction and Preſervation of <hi>Ireland.</hi> I ſhall now proceed to ſet down how palpably and remarkably it doth contribute to the <hi>Advancement of Trade,</hi> which is the Glory, Strength, and Security of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation; the Fountain and Source of the Riches, Wealth, and Plenty, which render it the Envy and Aſtoniſhment of all the Neighbouring Kingdoms: and without which, it were impoſſible to provide Suſtenance for the innume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Company of Inhabitants, wherewith the <hi>Country</hi> is ſufficiently <hi>furniſhed,</hi> and the <hi>Cities</hi> and <hi>Towns</hi> are ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely <hi>crowded.</hi> It is <hi>Trade</hi> that preſerves the Body Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litick in health, by <hi>Recreation</hi> and <hi>Exerciſe;</hi> by <hi>Evacua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> and <hi>Repletion,</hi> carrying off ſuch Things as are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neceſſary and redundant, and bringing in a conſtant ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply of whatſoever is uſeful and profitable. It is <hi>Trade</hi> that <hi>ranſacks the Indies,</hi> joins remote Iſlands in an ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginary <hi>Contiguity</hi> with <hi>England,</hi> and makes the whole World but a large <hi>Mart</hi> for Negotiation and Traffic. <hi>Trade</hi> is the Blood that Circulates in the <hi>Veins</hi> and <hi>Arteries</hi> of the Commonwealth, and diſperſeth the animal Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits to all the Limbs and extreme parts of the Body.</p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:97108:13"/>
               <p>This ſo neceſſary an Ingredient to the Honour and Felicity of <hi>England,</hi> has been ſignally augmented and improved by the <hi>Trade of Ireland</hi> co-incident with it, will ſuffer a mighty Detriment by the preſent <hi>Obſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction</hi> of Commerce, and will as eminently gain by its <hi>Revival</hi> and Recovery. The Advantage to <hi>Trade</hi> ariſing from <hi>Ireland</hi> is demonſtrable by theſe Particulars.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. The Scituation.</item>
                  <item>2. The Exportation.</item>
                  <item>3. The Importation.</item>
                  <item>4. The Ingenuity of the Inhabitants.</item>
                  <item>5. The Benefit to the King.</item>
               </list>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>I.</hi> The Scituation.</head>
                  <p>In the Deſcription of <hi>Ireland</hi> I might expatiate in recounting the many Benefits and Advantages which it enjoys <hi>in Common</hi> with her Neighbour Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, and the ſeveral Immunities which God and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture have indulged to it <hi>in peculiar</hi> above other Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; in its exemption from poyſonous Inſects, and noxious Vermin, as <hi>Frogs, Toads, Snakes, and Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, Neuts, Effs, and hurtful Spiders;</hi> but above all, in the Freedom from <hi>Moles,</hi> which are the <hi>Epidemical Nuſance of England,</hi> and are ſo ſenſibly injurious to Orchards, Gardens, Medows, and Paſtures; in a temperate and benign Air; in an infinite number of Fountains, Springs, Loughs (or Lakes) and freſh Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers; in an incredible ſtore and variety of Land and Sea-Fowls; (among which I would mention the incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible Number of <hi>Woodcocks,</hi> and how the Parſon of <hi>Clowniſh</hi> farms the Tyth of the <hi>Woodcocks</hi> catcht in
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:97108:14"/>his Pariſh at thirty Pounds <hi>per annum;</hi> where they are generally ſold at Twelve-Pence <hi>per</hi> dozen; the innumerable Flocks of <hi>Swans</hi> and <hi>Barnacles</hi> that haunt the River of <hi>Loughfoyl,</hi> but that it would ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude the wonder due to the reſt.) But becauſe theſe Priviledges are inherent to the Soil, and not commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicable to the Uſe and Benefit of the Neighbours, I ſhall paſs over the further commemoration of thoſe Matters, and apply my ſelf to the Rehearſal of ſuch Particulars only, as render <hi>Ireland</hi> in its happy Scituati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a moſt deſirable Countrey, and highly advantageous in its Acceſſion to the Crown of <hi>England.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Poſſibly there is not a Country in the whole World ſo admirably accommodated with <hi>convenient Bays, ſafe Harbours, large Havens, and uſeful Creeks;</hi> and that not only in ſome Sides and Corners, but quite round the Iſland. To deſcribe the Harbours of <hi>Carlingford, Strangford,</hi> the <hi>Lough of Carricfergus, Donaghadee, Loghlern, Raghlin, Portruſh, Lough-foyl, Lough-ſwilly, Sheep-Haven, Castledow, Killebeggs, Ballyſhannon, Sli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go,</hi> and <hi>Black-Sod</hi> in the <hi>North</hi> and <hi>Weſt Parts; Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, Lymerick, Trallee, Dingle, Kilmar, the Great Bay of Bantry,</hi> (including <hi>Bere Haven,</hi> and many others) <hi>Ship-Haven, Crook-Haven, Baltimore, Caſtle-Haven, Caſtlemain,</hi> the matchleſs Haven of <hi>Kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſale,</hi> the noble River of <hi>Cork, Yoghal, Dungarvan, Waterford, Slade, Wexford, Arclo, Dublin,</hi> &amp;c. in the <hi>South</hi> and <hi>Eaſtern</hi> Parts; beſide almoſt innumerable <hi>Creeks, Ports,</hi> and commodious <hi>Landing-Places,</hi> would take up more room than I have allowed to the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge of this brief Narration; my Purpoſe is only to mention them, referring the Account of their Beauty, Strength, Security, and Conveniency, to <hi>Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorians</hi> and <hi>Geographers.</hi> I ſhall only take notice, that as they are moſt advantageouſly placed for the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:97108:14"/>Trade of that Kingdom; ſo they are upon many Accounts a ſecure Refuge and Safeguard to their Friends and Allies, which is briefly demonſtrated in this, that none of the Neighbouring Countries can manage a Trade into the <hi>South, North,</hi> or <hi>Weſtern</hi> Seas, but they muſt be under great <hi>Danger of Ireland,</hi> if they be <hi>Enemies to England,</hi> or be beholding to it if they be in Amity; where upon every Turn they may meet with a ſafe Retreat from <hi>Storms</hi> and <hi>Tempeſts,</hi> and a ready Protection from <hi>Pirates</hi> and <hi>Robbers;</hi> it being ſet as a <hi>Watch-Tower</hi> in the Sea, within whoſe view all Ships muſt come that ſail and trade that way to any part of the World; an Iſland commodiouſly ſeated for the Dominion of the Seas, ſo long as ſhe is in one Intereſt with <hi>England.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>It is beyond the Power of Expreſſion to repeat the Advantages ariſing to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Trade by the relief and ſhelter of the <hi>Iriſh Harbours,</hi> where the ſeveral Fleets bound for the <hi>Streights,</hi> and for the <hi>Eaſt</hi> or <hi>Weſt Indies,</hi> or returning from thence, meet with Refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Security from all ſorts of Danger. This the Merchants find in their daily Voyages: This the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders of the Kings Ships can evidence upon frequent Experience; but I ſhall produce only one undeniable Inſtance, how highly and indeſpenſably it imports the <hi>Safety,</hi> as well as <hi>Trade</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> to preſerve <hi>Ireland</hi> to themſelves: That in the time of King <hi>Charles</hi> II. when <hi>England</hi> was imbroyl'd in an unlucky War with the <hi>States of Holland,</hi> not only a Fleet of Merchant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, conſiſting of an hundred Sail or thereabout, bound homeward from the <hi>Weſt-Indies</hi> and the <hi>Streights,</hi> but alſo forty Men of War (under the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of Sir <hi>Jeremy Smith</hi>) after that unfortunate Buſineſs at <hi>Chatham,</hi> came all into the Habour of <hi>Kinſale,</hi> where they continued in that Safety and
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:97108:15"/>Security, which they could not promiſe to themſelves in any Harbour or Port of <hi>England.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>2.</hi> The Exportation of <hi>Iriſh</hi> Commodities.</head>
                  <p>As <hi>Ireland</hi> is placed as an <hi>Out-guard</hi> to watch all <hi>Interlopers</hi> in the Trade of <hi>England,</hi> ſo lately it was a <hi>Store-houſe</hi> and <hi>Magazine</hi> to furniſh it. It ſent over yearly vaſt quantities of <hi>Wooll,</hi> ſhipt from the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Ports in <hi>Munster</hi> and <hi>Lemſter,</hi> which mightily ſupported the <hi>Staple</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> by the old and new <hi>Draperies,</hi> and other <hi>woollen Manufactures</hi> wrought and made in the Weſt Countrey: whereby not only a numerous Train of Families were fed and maintained, but an extraordinary addition was made to the Kings Revenue, by the Importation of it, when raw and unwrought, into <hi>England,</hi> and the Exportation of it, after it was wrought, into ſeveral Countries, to the great inriching of Merchants and Adventurers.</p>
                  <p>The Iſlands and Plantations in <hi>America</hi> are in a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner wholly ſuſtain'd by the vaſt quantities of <hi>Beef, Pork, Butter,</hi> and other Proviſions of the Product of <hi>Ireland:</hi> from whence an unſpeakable Benefit redounds to <hi>England</hi> by the vaſt Cargoes of the Goods of the ſaid Plantations returnd thither, and the Great Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption of thoſe Goods being ſhipt out of <hi>England</hi> into <hi>Ireland,</hi> than which nothing more evidently tends to the inriching the Merchants who trade into thoſe Parts, or to the increaſe of Shipping, or encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement to Navigation.</p>
                  <p>The mighty Quantities of <hi>Tallow, Hides, tann'd Leather, Skins</hi> of ſeveral ſorts, <hi>Yarn, Hemp, Linnen-Cloth, Cony-Skins,</hi> and other <hi>Furrs,</hi> yearly ſhipt from <hi>Ireland,</hi> and exported into <hi>England,</hi> ſupply that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom with the ſaid Commodities at very reaſonable
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:97108:15"/>Rates (which otherwiſe would prove exceſſive dear) to the great conveniency of the Inhabitants in general, and the particular <hi>Advantage</hi> of the <hi>Merchants</hi> and ſuch as trade in them.</p>
                  <p>The Cargoes of <hi>Salmon, Herrings, Pilchards,</hi> (and thoſe the beſt and faireſt to be had in any Part of the World) <hi>Eels,</hi> and other <hi>Fiſh</hi> made up yearly in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and tranſported into ſeveral Parts in <hi>Spain,</hi> to <hi>Venice,</hi> and all the Ports in the <hi>Mediterranean</hi> Sea, would ſtartle common Belief. I have heard from faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Relation, and I ſpoke of it before, that in the <hi>South</hi> of <hi>Ireland,</hi> they have made in a year near Eight hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred <hi>Tuns of Pilchards:</hi> A Perſon of great <hi>Quality,</hi> (whoſe Judgment and Credit no man will diſpute) did aver to me, that in one Seaſon 16000. <abbr>
                        <hi>l.</hi>
                     </abbr> was paid for the <hi>Pilchards</hi> taken on the <hi>South ſide of Cork,</hi> and the moſt of it by Sir <hi>John Frederic</hi> of <hi>London.</hi> That in one Port in the <hi>North,</hi> called <hi>Dunfanaghan,</hi> they have made in one Seaſon Two thouſand <hi>Tuns of Herrings.</hi> And I was told by a very honeſt and intelligent Perſon, (who in the Reign of <hi>Charles the Second</hi> was <hi>Collector</hi> of the Port of <hi>London-Derry</hi>) that in that one Place there was ſhipt off in one Seaſon 450. <hi>Tuns of Salmon,</hi> 400. <hi>Tuns of Herrings,</hi> and 80. <hi>Tuns of Eels:</hi> The Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit and Profit of all which accrues to the Merchants of <hi>England,</hi> on whoſe ſole Account almoſt all the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned Commodities are ſhipt off and ſent away, to the great increaſe of their Shipping, and the mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt incouragement of Navigation,</p>
                  <p>Theſe things being undenyable, and perfectly true in matter of Fact, and which I am conſtrained by the neceſſity of the Argument to mention over again, it is evident beyond Contradiction, that the <hi>Trade of Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> is of ineſtimable Advantage to the <hi>Trade of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> highly contributing, if not wholly ſubſervient to it.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:97108:16"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>3.</hi> The Importation of <hi>Engliſh</hi> Commodities.</head>
                  <p>The great multitudes of Goods and Commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities continually exported out of <hi>Ireland</hi> into <hi>England,</hi> did not more apparently tend to the <hi>Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of Trade</hi> there, than the continual Importation of all kinds of Wares and Merchandiſe from thence. The People of <hi>Ireland</hi> did not deal like Niggards, or Rooks, to vend and put off the Product of their own Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and not be inſtrumental to promote the Conſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of what their Neighbours had to ſpare; on the contrary they maintain'd a conſtant Correſpondence, and an univerſal Commerce, and hugely <hi>advanced the Trade of England.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The <hi>Wooll</hi> which they from time to time ſent into <hi>England,</hi> they received again (and perhaps with it much of the growth there) transformed into the old and the new <hi>Drapery,</hi> and all ſorts of <hi>Woollen Manufa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures,</hi> and thereby doubly advanced the <hi>Engliſh Trade,</hi> by the <hi>Outlet,</hi> and by the <hi>Return,</hi> by ſelling the one, and buying the other</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Silks</hi> wrought, and un-wrought; <hi>Gold</hi> and <hi>Silver Lace; Buttons; Ribbands,</hi> &amp;c. all ſorts of <hi>Grocery, Spicery, Haberdaſhers</hi> and <hi>Milliners Ware; Beavers</hi> and other fine <hi>Hats; Tobacco</hi> cut and dry'd, in Rowl, and in Leaf; <hi>white Salt; Coals;</hi> and many foreign Commodities, were daily and hourly brought in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all the Ports of <hi>Ireland,</hi> being purchaſed by the Merchants there from the Merchants of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, Briſtol, Cheſter, Leverpool, Plymouth,</hi> and other Towns and Cities in <hi>England;</hi> the Quantities whereof muſt be prodigiouſly great, to ſupply not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the <hi>Neceſſities,</hi> but the <hi>Vanity</hi> and <hi>Luxury</hi> of ſo po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulous and opulent a Kingdom, (the Rate of whoſe Expences was no way regulated by the inſtinct of
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:97108:16"/>
                     <hi>Thrift,</hi> or <hi>Parſimony</hi>) and conſequently the <hi>Gains and Profit</hi> redounding to the <hi>Engliſh Merchants</hi> muſt in rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon bear ſome Proportion with the <hi>Vent and Conſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;</hi> the eſtimate whereof in a few years is beyond <hi>Credit,</hi> if not paſt <hi>Numeration.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I could appeal to particular Men by Name, whoſe Books and Accounts will juſtifie my Poſition, that <hi>England</hi> received incredible Advantage by their Trade with <hi>Ireland,</hi> and their ſenſible diſappointments in the preſent Ceſſation of Trade from thence, do too unhappily confirm it; but I will not do that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice to them, to diſcover the Secrets of their Deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or raiſe a Spirit of Envy at their proſperous Proceedings: I honour them for their Ingenuity; I applaud their Induſtry, and heartily wiſh them rein<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtated in their former Courſe of Traffick, that all Men may be convinced by their Experiment, how advantageouſly the <hi>Trade of Ireland</hi> co-operates to the <hi>Advancement of the Trade of</hi> England.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>4.</hi> The Ingenuity of the Inhabitants.</head>
                  <p>I am now brought to a hard <hi>Dilemma;</hi> I muſt ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther renounce the Country, from whence I came, or retract my Aſſertion: For when I go about to il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtrate <hi>the Ingenuity of the Inhabitants,</hi> I <hi>confute</hi> my ſelf, by a <hi>Diſcourſe ſo void of it.</hi> But there is <hi>no ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Rule without ſome Exceptions;</hi> and I hope that my particular <hi>Defects</hi> ſhall not be imputed as a dero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation from the <hi>Credit</hi> of the reſt.</p>
                  <p>It is an ungrateful Imployment to make Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſons, and I do not in the leaſt intend any unkind Reflection upon the Common People of <hi>England,</hi> when I alledge, that the ordinary and vulgar ſort of the <hi>Britiſh</hi> Inhabitants in <hi>Ireland</hi> are much more In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genious and quick, more docible, more intelligent in
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:97108:17"/>the Laws and Cuſtoms of the Country; more active, ſedulous and inquiſitive; diſpoſed to handle the <hi>Sword</hi> as well as the <hi>Plough,</hi> and notably capable to ſerve upon Juries, and to diſcharge the Duty in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbent on them at Aſſiſes and Seſſions. But I ſhall only inſiſt on that Qualification which is more proper and pertinent to the Argument in hand, <hi>viz.</hi> their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Diſpoſition to Trade, and an undefatigable In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry in promoting it, and all for the advantage of the Trade of <hi>England.</hi> For the <hi>Petty Chapmen,</hi> Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders in ſmall Towns, and Country Dealers, are only <hi>Hawkers, Procurers,</hi> and <hi>Brokers</hi> for the greater Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants in Cities and big Towns; and they ordinarily make themſelves <hi>Factors</hi> for the Merchants in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi> ſending over to them the moſt Part of what they gather; or bringing back from them the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities of <hi>England</hi> in return of what they adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and gain upon their own Account. Thus I have obſerved the <hi>Chapmen</hi> in a ſmall <hi>Village</hi> (belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to my ſelf) with great Art and Ingenuity ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotiating with the Neighbours about them, making up many Tuns of Butter, and Tallow, gathering great quantities of <hi>Yarn, Linnen cloth, Salt, Hides,</hi> and <hi>Tann'd Leather;</hi> which ſoon after they ſell to the Merchants in the next City or Sea-Port, who ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther deal by <hi>Commiſſion</hi> from the Merchants in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> or export them on their own Account, but cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly bring home the <hi>Produce,</hi> in the Wares and Merchandiſe of <hi>England,</hi> (and I know one particular Man, who in one Town in one Seaſon, made up Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven hundred Tuns of Butter by Commiſſion, and as a <hi>Factor</hi> for ſome Merchants there) but which way ſoever it be, the Ingenuity and Diligence of the Inhabitants of <hi>Ireland</hi> does indiſputably advance the Trade of <hi>England,</hi> and the whole Labour of the one centers in the Benefit of the other.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="section">
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:97108:17"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>5.</hi> The Benefit to the King.</head>
                  <p>Tho' I propoſe the Kings Benefit in the laſt Place, yet it is not the leaſt of my Care and good Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes; and I perſwade my ſelf that the Loyal and Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Subjects of <hi>England</hi> will on that very Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (if there were no other Motives to incite them) account <hi>Ireland</hi> worth the keeping, and accordingly will employ their Wealth, and exert their Courage and Strength for the ſpeedy <hi>Reduction</hi> and Reſtitution of it. To inforce this, I need produce no other Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, than the repetition of what was before remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated; That the annual <hi>Revenue of Ireland</hi> coming into the Treaſury and the Kings Coffers, amounted to <hi>Three hundred and forty thouſand Pounds,</hi> out of which, beſide the neceſſary Exhibition; for ſupporting the State and ſafety of the Kingdom, a very conſiderable Sum was yearly laid at the Kings Feet, therewith to gratifie ſuch Servitors and Favourites in <hi>England,</hi> as the Revenue there would not reach to ſupply. To which let me add, that though under <hi>Charles the Second,</hi> the <hi>proteſtant Intereſt in Ireland</hi> received as little Incouragement as could be expected under a <hi>Proteſtant King;</hi> yet <hi>thriving</hi> by their <hi>Pruning,</hi> ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king <hi>deeper Root</hi> by their being <hi>ſhaken,</hi> and growing more <hi>ſtrong by their Depreſſion;</hi> they had, beyond all Doubt, added before this time a very valuable Aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation to the Publick Revenue, by their <hi>Trade and Improvements,</hi> had not <hi>Popery nipt them,</hi> and <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrary Power blasted them.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:97108:18"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>3.</hi> The danger of falling into the hands of the <hi>French.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Let us now reflect upon what has been ſaid, and Re capitulate the <hi>skatter'd</hi> Arguments hinted in this abrupt and immethodical Diſcourſe. If neither the <hi>ſenſe of Shame,</hi> the <hi>Purſuit of Fame and Glory,</hi> the <hi>Influence</hi> of Brotherly <hi>Charity,</hi> the <hi>Sympathy with Blood and Kindred,</hi> the <hi>Reſpect to Religion,</hi> the <hi>Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſition of Wealth,</hi> the <hi>Support of Trade,</hi> the <hi>Increaſe</hi> of the <hi>Publick Revenue,</hi> nor the irreſiſtible motive of <hi>Self-Preſervation,</hi> can prove Inducements ſufficient to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the People of <hi>England</hi> to a hearty, affectionate, and vigorous eſpouſing of the <hi>Protestant Cauſe in Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> by a timely Proſecution of a War there, and root<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out <hi>the last Remains of Popery;</hi> let us change the <hi>Scene,</hi> and ſuppoſe <hi>Ireland</hi> ſubdued by the preſent In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaders, and become a Province to <hi>France,</hi> (which God of his infinite Mercy avert) then without all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adventure theſe miſchiefs will inevitably enſue.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The <hi>French King</hi> having an inſatiable Thirſt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the univerſal <hi>Monarchy of Europe,</hi> and retaining an implacable Reſolution to deſtroy <hi>all ſorts of Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stants,</hi> and utterly to root out <hi>that Pestilent Northern Hereſie;</hi> abounding in Wealth and Treaſure, follow'd by mighty Armies, ſtrengthned by a numerous Fleet of Ships; as nothing in humane Probability can de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feat his execrable Deſigns of Aggrandiſing himſelf by the Ruin of his Neighbours, but the ſcarcity of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient <hi>Ports and Havens</hi> in any of his Dominions; ſo it muſt be his Principal Aim and endeavour to be <hi>Master of Ireland;</hi> whereby he will be ſufficiently ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodated with excellent good Harbours, in which he may ſecurely place his Fleet, to extend his <hi>Soveraignty over the Seas,</hi> and opportunely annoy his Enemies.</p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:97108:18"/>
               <p n="2">2. This being accompliſh'd, not only the <hi>Revenue and Trade of Ireland</hi> will be utterly loſt, the Auxili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary Aid of <hi>two hundred thouſand Protestants</hi> diverted and taken away, and many thouſands of them for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to depend upon the <hi>Charity of England:</hi> the <hi>Trade to America,</hi> and all the <hi>Weſtern Iſlands</hi> will not only be intercepted, but in a ſhort time thoſe Countries be wholly conquered and reduced to the Poſſeſſion of the <hi>French,</hi> and annexed to his <hi>Dominion,</hi> and made a <hi>Prey</hi> to glut his reſtleſs Ambition.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The <hi>French King</hi> will make <hi>Ireland</hi> a Maga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zine and Store-houſe for the victualling His Ships, and the <hi>Harbours</hi> as ſo many <hi>Docks</hi> to ſhelter them, where his Fleet riding in ſafety, an Opportunity will be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven him, not only to ingroſs all manner of <hi>Trade,</hi> but that of <hi>England</hi> will be intirely interrupted, if not infallibly deſtroyed; ſince no Ships can peep out from thence in their Navigation toward the Streights, or to the <hi>Indies,</hi> but they muſt paſs within view of ſome Ports of <hi>Ireland,</hi> or very near them, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly muſt be expoſed to the Attacks of that rapacious <hi>Leviathan,</hi> or be neceſſitated to ſail in great Fleets, and very ſtrong Convoys under <hi>Frigats</hi> and <hi>Men of VVar,</hi> to the ineſtimable charge of the <hi>State,</hi> and detriment to the Merchants of <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. Let it be conſider'd, that ſince <hi>VVooll</hi> and <hi>VVoollen Manufactures</hi> are the ancient <hi>Staple of England,</hi> and a main ſupport to their trading into all Foreign Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, if it ſhould ſo come to paſs, that <hi>Ireland</hi> be aliena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from it, which abounds with that Commodity, and from whence it may be exported at far cheaper Rates than can be afforded in <hi>England;</hi> how unſpeakable a Prejudice will it be to the <hi>Trade?</hi> How will it impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veriſh the People, and bring an unavoidable ruin on many <hi>Towns</hi> and <hi>Families?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:97108:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p n="5">5. Tho it is to be hoped that the Power of <hi>France,</hi> with the Addition of <hi>Ireland,</hi> ſhall never be able to make a <hi>Conquest of England;</hi> nevertheleſs by ſuch an unwelcom Neighbourhood, it is more than probable the <hi>French King</hi> may diſcompoſe the Peace and Quiet of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> when at any time of the year he can tranſport an Army from <hi>Ireland,</hi> or land ſmall Forces in <hi>North VVales</hi> in ſix hours time, in <hi>South-VVales</hi> in twelve, or in the ſpace of four Hours in the <hi>VVeſt</hi> of <hi>Scotland:</hi> And this not to be prevented by the <hi>Engliſh Fleet,</hi> or by all the Art and Contrivance of Mankind.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <head>The CONCL<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SION.</head>
               <p>I wiſh the People of <hi>England</hi> may ſee now in this their Day, what belongs to their Peace, before it be hid from their Eyes; That they may not be deluded by falſe Gloſſes, and ſiniſter Interpretations of Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Acts, nor be cajol'd by jealous Miſpriſions and groundleſs Cenſures on private Councils: That they may underſtand, and conſider how much their ſafety and the Intereſt of the Proteſtant Religion is concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and involved in the Fate of <hi>Ireland;</hi> and that if the Enemy chance to poſſeſs the Out-works, the City will be in great danger: That they may not be abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by Chimerical Notions of <hi>Obeying without Reſerve,</hi> or being deſtroyed without Reſiſtance: That they would reſt contented with obtaining their Deſires, in being happy under the Eſtabliſhment of a Proteſtant King and Queen, and not hanker after a Change, or be bewitched to make a wanton Experiment of Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence and Protection under a Popiſh Government.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:97108:19"/>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
